Speaker 1 (higher-pitched voice): Today's hearing on child care since the pandemic, macroeconomic impacts of public policy measures. I want to get right to the point. Federal child care funding is on the verge of a massive funding cliff. This cliff has the potential to cause more than three million children across this country
Speaker 1 (higher-pitched voice): to lose their care, and the impacts will ripple throughout our whole economy.
Speaker 2 (higher-pitched voice): But here's the kicker. We here in Congress have the power to stop this. And that's why we're having today's hearing, and that's why I am so happy that we have our witnesses here today: Glenn Hopkins, who runs a child care
Speaker 3: center; Sarah Hardy, co-founder and COO of an infant formula company; and Catherine Edwards, an economist and an expert on the labor market.
Speaker 3: They
Speaker 2 (higher-pitched voice): are here to help explain what the looming child care cliff will mean for businesses, for their
Speaker 4: workers, for parents and families, and for our whole economy.
Three
Speaker 1 (higher-pitched voice): years ago, in the early weeks of the pandemic, thousands of child care centers were forced to close their doors. These closures exposed
a
Speaker 4: truth that millions of American families already knew. The child care system in America is badly broken.
Speaker 2 (higher-pitched voice): For decades, millions of working families have struggled to find care for their children, and if they are fortunate enough to find good care, millions struggle
Speaker 3: to pay for it so they can go to work or to school. Access to high-quality child care is essential to our
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): economy. If mamas and daddies can't get care for their babies, they can't go to work. And if millions of parents can't go to work,
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): Businesses can't find the workers they need to
Speaker 6: operate. And if businesses cut back because they can't find workers, then national productivity and economic growth
suffer.
Speaker 1 (higher-pitched voice): These realities hit especially hard during the pandemic. When the entire childcare industry was on the verge of total collapse, Senator Tina Smith
Speaker 4: and I rang the alarm bell.
Speaker 4: Democrats in Congress responded to this threat
by
Speaker 1 (higher-pitched voice): providing $50 billion in federal funding to help stabilize the childcare industry. Now, this
Speaker 3: funding couldn't possibly solve every problem, but it worked, and it kept the industry afloat.
Speaker 3: Child care providers used those funds to help pay for rent, to keep
Speaker 4: children and workers safe, to raise wages, to alleviate the massive funding shortages, and much, much more.
And
Speaker 6: millions of children got the care they needed.
But
Speaker 6: now the child care industry is back on the brink of disaster. Most of the child care relief funding
Speaker 4: expires at the end of September, that's just 10 days from now. So what will it mean for American families if we don't invest more in child care?
Speaker 1 (higher-pitched voice): Analysts estimate that 70,000 child care programs will close.
Speaker 1 (higher-pitched voice): That means nearly a quarter of a million child care workers
Speaker 4: could lose their jobs and over 3 million children could lose their care. Millions of parents, especially
Speaker 3: moms, will be forced to leave the labor force at a time when we're already facing an incredibly tight labor market. The ripple effects will be
Speaker 6: far-reaching and devastating.
We
Speaker 6: cannot let this happen. We must act, and we must act quickly.
Speaker 3: We have champions in the Senate willing to get this done. Last month, I joined Senator Kane, Smith, and 27 of our colleagues calling for $16 billion in emergency federal funding so child care providers can keep their doors open.
Speaker 3: Just last week, the White House announced support for efforts to secure additional funding for child care, and I'm willing to reach across the aisle to work with any Republican who wants to help get this done. We've got one big opportunity before us this month.
Speaker 4: In August, the administration sent its supplemental emergency spending requests for Ukraine disaster relief and more.
The
Speaker 4: Senate has now
Speaker 6: started a debate on that package, and by the end of the month, we need to reach an agreement to fund the government
Speaker 4: and prevent a shutdown.
This is
Speaker 4: a must-pass bill. We
need to
Speaker 4: keep the government going so that we can continue food safety inspections
Speaker 3: and vital medical research. We must protect our national security interests in Ukraine and around the world. We have to respond to the natural disasters that have devastated communities around the nation,
including
Speaker 3: in Massachusetts, and we cannot leave American families behind. We need long-term investments in child care, and we must at least keep the child care industry from tumbling off a devastating cliff. Once again, I want to thank the members of this committee and I thank our witnesses for helping to make clear the importance of
Speaker 6: this investment in America's families.